# Orianna DeMasi

## Overview

My current research focuses on dialogue systems and my graduate research applied machine learning methods to develop and evaluate tools specifically for mental health. I enjoy working on multi-disciplinary teams with complex datasets and am especially concerned with whether computational methods are reliable and effective in important real-world applications.

#### Education

2019 **Ph.D. Computer Science**, University of California, Berkeley.

Evaluation of Methods for Data-Driven Tools that Empower Mental Health Professionals

2009 B.Sc. Mathematics, McGill University.

## Experience

2019-2021 University of California, Davis, Postdoctoral Researcher, Computer Science.

- Working on conversational agents and text generation.
- Developed, trained, evaluated neural net generation + retrieval framework with GPT-2 to improve persona-consistency and text diversity to simulate users and train hotline counselors.
- Used linear models to assess consequences of errors in chatbot counseling contexts.
- Helped design dataset and model evaluation for peer-support chat agent (in submission).
- $\bullet\,$  Developed course assignment for ethical implications of open-domain chatbot.
- Built, deployed chatbots + websites for 3 interactive user studies and dataset collection.
- Collaborated on multi-disciplinary teams with various stakeholders.

2012-2019 University of California, Berkeley, Graduate Student Researcher, Electrical Engineering and Computer Sciences.

- Thesis focused on using computational methods to build tools for mental health professionals.
- Engineered features and developed machine learning models with time series of mobile phone sensors to predict user wellbeing, e.g., mood.
- Developed framework to rigorously evaluate machine learning model predictions on longitudinal patient data with statistical permutation tests.
- Collaborated with researchers in UCSF Psychiatry to evaluate an SMS texting program to improve outcomes for CBT therapy to treat clinical depression. Used Mann–Whitney U tests, mixed-effects linear models to analyze patient responses in an RCT.
- Designed, collected, cleaned, and curated complex, messy datasets of various data types.
- Led, collaborated on, and communicated with multi-disciplinary teams, including crisis counselors and clinicians, to run 2 user studies, 1 RCT, and 1 survey.

- 2015-2016 Twitter Inc, Data Science Intern, Business Insights Team.
  - Developed clustering framework for hashtag communities.
  - Identified hashtag communities with increased engagement.
  - Wrote paper nominated for Best Paper at ICWSM '16.
- 2010-2012 **Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory**, Computer Systems Engineer, Complex Systems Group.

Mathematical cyber-security project. Worked on using machine learning to identify what code was being run on supercomputers as a potential way to monitor allocation usage.

- 2009 McGill University, Research Assistant.
  - Worked with Professor Tony Humphries to study a delay differential equation with two state dependent delays (SDDE).
- 2008 **Texas A&M University**, Research Experience for Undergraduates.

  Worked with John Walton and Yuliya Gorb to model the migration of coyotes in the US.
- 2007 Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute, Summer Student Fellowship. Worked with Steve Lentz to model tidal dynamics near Cape Cod.

#### Selected Publications

- O. DeMasi, Y. Li, Z. Yu A Multi-Persona Chatbot for Hotline Counselor Training. EMNLP Findings (2020)
- CA. Figueroa, O. DeMasi, R. Hernandez-Ramos, and A. Aguilera Who benefits most from adding technology to depression treatment and how? An analysis of engagement with a texting adjunct for psychotherapy. Journal of Telemedicine and e-Health. (2020)
- O. DeMasi, A. Paxton, and K. Koy Ad Hoc Efforts for Advancing Data Science Education PLOS Computational Biology. (2020)
- O. DeMasi, M. Hearst, and B. Recht Towards Augmenting Crisis Counselor Training by Improving Message Retrieval NAACL workshop on Computational Linguistics and Clinical Psychology. (2019)
- O. DeMasi, K. Kording, and B. Recht *Meaningless comparisons lead to false optimism in medical machine learning.* PLOS One. (2017) http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0184604
- O. DeMasi, S. Feygin, A. Dembo, A. Aguilera, and B. Recht Wellbeing Tracking via Smartphone Measured Activity and Sleep: Cohort Study. JMIR Mhealth Uhealth. (2017) http://dx.doi.org/10.2196/mhealth.7820
- O. DeMasi and B. Recht An example of how false conclusions could be made with personalized health tracking and suggestions for avoiding similar situations. Data for Good Exchange. (2017)
- O. DeMasi and B. Recht A Step Towards Quantifying When an Algorithm Can and Cannot Predict an Individual's Wellbeing. Ubicomp Workshop on Mental Health: Sensing and Intervention. (2017)
- A. Aguilera, E. Bruehlman-Senecal, O. DeMasi, P. Avila Automated text messaging adjunct to CBT treatment increases attendance and reduces attrition. JMIR. (2017) http://www.jmir.org/2017/5/e148

- O. DeMasi, A. Aguilera, B. Recht Detecting Change in Depressive Symptoms from Daily Wellbeing Questions, Personality, and Activity. Wireless Health. (2016)
- O. DeMasi, D. Mason, J. Ma Understanding Communities via Hashtag Engagement: A Clustering Based Approach. International Conference on Web and Social Media. (2016) [Best paper nominee, 17% acceptance rate]
- O. DeMasi, J. Gonzalez, B. Recht, J. Demmel, *Using Bayesian Optimization for Hardware Design*. Workshop on Bayesian Optimization, NIPS. (2014) http://bayesopt.github.io/papers/paper3.pdf
- A.R. Humphries, O. DeMasi, et al. Dynamics of a Delay Differential Equation With Multiple State Dependent Delays. DCDS-A. (2012)

http://www.math.mcgill.ca/humphries/research/papers/DCDS-A7.pdf

### Awards

- 2018 **EECS Rising Stars invited participant**, Massachusetts Institute of Technology. Selective workshop for women considering academic careers in EECS.
- 2016-2018 **Data Science Fellowship**, Berkeley Institute for Data Science. Fellowship for two years of graduate research.
  - 2018 First place award, Big Ideas innovation competition, UC Berkeley. Connected Communities category.
  - 2017 **Tech for Social Good Fellowship**, The Center for Information Technology Research in the Interest of Society (CITRIS), UC Berkeley.

    Research project funding.
  - 2014 Mobile App Challenge, Center for Information Technology Research in the Interest of Society (CITRIS), UC Berkeley.
    Award for developing the MoodStreamer smartphone application.
- 2012-2016 ARCS Graduate Fellowship, ARCS Foundation, Northern California chapter. Full support for four years of graduate research.
  - 2012 Excellence Award, Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Sciences, UC Berkeley.
  - 2009 Summer Undergraduate Research Award, McGill University.
- 2006-2007 Fellowship for Outstanding Scholarship, Western Connecticut State University.

## Teaching

- 2017-2018 Fung Fellowship for Wellness and Technology Innovations, School of Public Health, UC Berkeley.
  - Teaching assistant to Jaspal Sandhu. Course focused on developing health and technology solutions with human-centered design.
  - 2016 Applications of Parallel Computing (graduate course), Department of EECS, UC Berkeley.
    - Teaching assistant to James Demmel.
  - 2014 Statistical Learning Theory (graduate course), Departments of EECS and Statistics, UC Berkeley.
    - Teaching assistant to Benjamin Recht.

2006-2009 **Grader and Tutor for various math courses**, McGill University and Western Connecticut State University.

Graded: Advanced Calculus (fall 2008), Numerical Analysis (fall 2009), Real Analysis (fall 2009). Tutored: McGill Help Desk, WCSU Tutoring Resource Center, WCSU Math Clinic.

# Academic Service

- 2021 Workshop organization, ICLR workshop on neural conversational agents.
- 2016-2020 Reviewer, EMNLP, JMIR, GigaScience, Ubicomp workshop mental health.
- 2010-2021 **Research Mentor**, I have mentored 18 students through independent reserach projects.
- 2018-2019 **Working group lead**, Berkeley Institute for Data Science Diversity and Inclusion Working Group.

We strive to increase diversity and promote inclusion within data science at UC Berkeley and the Open Source Software community. Together we designed and organized a workshop series to encourage and support under-represented undergraduates pursue data science.

- Working group member, Education and Training Working Group.Group at the Berkeley Institute for Data Science focused on expanding data science education.
- 2016-2017 **Co-president**, Women in Computer Science and Electrical Engineering (WICSE). Computer Science co-president leading networking, promotion, and outreach for women in EE and CS organization.
- 2012-2016 Outreach Mentor, Graduate Pathways Symposium, Black Girls Code, Technovation.
- 2015-2016 Industrial Liaison, Women in Computer Science and Electrical Engineering.
- 2014-2015 **Treasurer**, Women in Computer Science and Electrical Engineering (WICSE).

#### Skills

Pytion (pandas, matplotlib, numpy, statsmodels, scikit-learn, flask, jupyter, pytorch, seaborn, parlai, transformers, rpy2), SQL, Bash, Git & GitHub, MTurk, HTML